Guide to the Walt Whitman papers, 1841-1940, bulk 1841-1891 RL.01378
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Walt Whitman papers
1841-1940, bulk 1841-1891
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
RL.01378
28 Linear Feet
Collection includes correspondence separated into two subseries: "Letters To or About Walt Whitman," and "Letters From or By Walt Whitman." Most of Whitman's letters in the collection were written between 1880 and 1891. Letters include those written to and from friends, family members, editors, publishers, and soldiers Whitman met in and around Washington, D. C. during the Civil War. The Clippings Series includes both large groups of clippings collected and annotated by Whitman, and clippings Whitman took from complete or nearly complete articles. Also included are manuscripts and printed materials about or relating to Whitman, most of which date during Whitman's lifetime. There are portraits, etchings, engravings, and sketches both of Whitman and of his brother, George, and sister, Hannah. A Writings Series contains manuscript and printed versions of poetry and prose dating from Whitman's career in journalism up to the end of his life. It is divided into four subseries: Manuscript Poems (1855-1882 and undated); Manuscript Prose (1852-1891 and undated); Proofs (1874-1891 and undated); and Periodicals Containing Contributions by Whitman (1841-1891).
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The bulk of Duke University's Walt Whitman holdings were acquired through a series of substantial donations made by Dr. and Mrs. Josiah C. Trent. Much of the Trent material was originally gathered by Richard Maurice Bucke, Whitman's friend and literary executor, who sold manuscript versions of his biography of Whitman, along with his collection of unpublished letters and Whitman's personal papers and books, in London in 1935. The next year, Jacob Schwartz offered for sale in New York a large portion of the Whitman holdings that had belonged to Bucke, and many of the items listed in the catalogue of this sale were a part of the original donation made to Duke by Dr. and Mrs. Trent in 1942. The Trent family made several important additions to their initial bequest in the years following the establishment of the collection, but Duke University does not expect its Whitman manuscript holdings to expand at any time in the near future.
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1819 May 31 Born Walter Whitman in West Hills, Huntington Township, N.Y. to Walter and Louisa (VanVelsor) Whitman
1823 Whitman family moved to Brooklyn
1825-1830 Attended Brooklyn public schools
1830-1831 Worked as office boy for lawyer and doctor
1831-1832 Printing apprentice for Long Island Patriot
1832-1835 Worked as compositor for Long Island Star
1836-1838 Taught school on Long Island
1838-1839 Worked on two newspapers, Long Islander and Long Island Democrat
1840 Campaigned for Martin Van Buren
1840-1841 Taught school on Long Island
1841 Moved to New York City; worked as compositor for The New World
1842-1845 Worked for and contributed to various newspapers in New York City
1845-1846 Returned to Brooklyn and worked for Evening Star
1846-1848 Edited Brooklyn's Daily Eagle
1848 Left Daily Eagle, went to New Orleans to edit Daily Crescent. Resigned and returned to Brooklyn.
1848-1849 Founded and edited Weekly Freeman, a "free-soil" newspaper
1849-1854 Operated printing office, bookstore, and house building business and did freelance journalism
1855 Copyrighted first edition of Leaves of Grass
1855-1856 Wrote for Life Illustrated; published second edition of Leaves of Grass
1857-1860 Edited Brooklyn Daily Times
1860 Published third edition of Leaves of Grass
1861-1862 Wrote freelance journalism; visited soldiers in New York Hospital; visited wounded brother in Fredericksburg
1863-1864 Moved to Washington, D.C.; worked as clerk in Army Paymaster's Office; visited military hospitals; returned to Brooklyn for 6 months in 1864
1865 Returned to Washington, D.C. and worked as clerk in Indian Bureau of Department of the Interior; began and suspended printing of Drum-Taps; discharged by Secretary James Harlan for writing "obscene" poetry; transferred to clerkship in Attorney General's Office; again published Drum-Taps and Sequel; began relationship with Peter Doyle
1866 William D. O'Connor published The Good Gray Poet, a defense co-written by Whitman in response to Whitman's firing by Harlan
1867 4th edition of Leaves of Grass published
1868 Poems of Walt Whitman published in London
1870 5th edition of Leaves of Grass published
1873 Suffered paralytic stroke; mother died on May 23rd; moved in with brother George in Camden, N.J.
1874 Discharged from his position in Washington, D.C.
1876 Published Centennial edition of Leaves of Grass and Two Rivulets, and Memoranda During the War; befriended Harry Stafford
1879 Gave first Lincoln lecture in New York
1882 Publicity concerning the suppression of Leaves of Grass in Boston resulted in unprecedented sales
1888 Suffered a second paralytic stroke; made will naming Richard Maurice Bucke, Thomas Harned, and Horace Traubel literary executors
1889 70th birthday commemorated in Camden's Compliment to Walt Whitman
1892 Died March 26th; buried in Harleigh Cemetery, Camden, N.J.
Collection Overview
The Walt Whitman papers incorporates material spanning the dates 1841-1940, with the bulk of the material dating from 1841-1891. The virtual reorganization of the collection, based upon that devised by Ellen F. Frey in A Bibliography of Walt Whitman (Port Washington, NY: Kennikat Press, 1945), divides it into six series: Correspondence, Writings, Clippings, Material About or Relating to Whitman, Portraits, and Miscellany.
Items marked as unavailable are currently missing.
Correspondence is separated into two subseries: "Letters To or About Walt Whitman," and "Letters From or By Walt Whitman." Most of Whitman's letters in the collection were written between 1880 and 1891. The Clippings Series lists both large groups of clippings collected and annotated by Whitman, and clippings Whitman took from complete or nearly complete articles. Whenever possible, these have been dated according to the periodical in which the articles originally appeared. Material About or Relating to Whitman is comprised of subseries that catalog manuscript versions of Richard Maurice Bucke's biography of Whitman, as well as other manuscript material written by Whitman or recorded by his friends. The Portraits Series includes formal photographic and painted portraits, etchings, engravings, and sketches, both of Whitman and of his brother, George, and sister, Hannah. The Miscellany consists of ephemera related to Whitman's life and career as a poet. Two scrapbooks, book wrappers for the first edition of Leaves of Grass, and documents relating to the Whitman fund are listed among this series' eclectic contents.
By far the largest series in the collection, the Writings Series contains manuscript and printed versions of poetry and prose dating from Whitman's career in journalism to the end of his life. It is divided into four subseries: Manuscript Poems (1855-1882 and undated); Manuscript Prose (1852-1891 and undated); Proofs (1874-1891 and undated); and Periodicals Containing Contributions by Whitman (1841-1891). The first subseries, "Manuscript Poems," is further subdivided into categories intended to define three separate levels of poetic composition: manuscript versions of poems that appear in at least one edition of Leaves of Grass, manuscript versions of poems not published in Leaves of Grass, and verse fragments and outlines. The researcher is advised to consult the NYU Collected Writings of Walt Whitman, particularly Harold W. Blodgett and Sculley Bradley, eds., Leaves of Grass: A Comprehensive Reader's Edition (New York: NYUP, 1965), pp. 585-706, for publication of previously uncollected material. Although older, Oscar Lovell Triggs, ed., Leaves of Grass by Walt Whitman, vol. 3 of 10 (New York: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1902) and Clarence Gohdes and Rollo G. Silver, eds., Faint Clews and Indirections: Manuscripts of Walt Whitman and His Family (Durham, NC: Duke UP, 1949) are also helpful, the former particularly when used alongside Frey's Bibliography.
The Manuscript Prose Subseries in the Writings Series is further divided into seven categories. The first three are comprised of manuscript versions of stories, prefaces, and essays and lectures, respectively. Four less distinct subheadings follow. "Notes on Literature" represents an almost exact transliteration of Frey's category of the same name, however it should be noted that this category does not, at the time of writing, list all of Trent's holdings in Whitman's literary-critical manuscripts. Some literary criticism is contained in "Autobiographical Manuscripts" and "Whitman on His Own Writings," along with more purely impressionistic self-reflection. "Miscellany" should also be consulted, as it brings together in an unsystematic way Whitman's notes on travel, reading, and education as well as a scattering of notes on poetry and different forms of literary production.
The last two subseries of the Writings Series bring together various published versions of Whitman's writing. Annotated proofs of his poetry and prose are identified in the finding aid, and cross-references are included between the Proofs Subseries and the Periodicals Containing Contributions by Whitman Subseries in instances where the collection lists both a proof and a published version of a poem or article among its headings. The Periodicals Containing Contributions by Whitman Subseries provides a survey of his writing during his lifetime.
Many published works by and about Walt Whitman and housed in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library have been cataloged individually. These can be found by searching the Duke online catalog.
American literature -- 19th century; Poets, American -- 19th century; Frey, Ellen Frances. Catalogue of the Whitman collection in the Duke University Library, 1945: t.p. (Ellen Frances Frey); Bucke, Richard Maurice, 1837-1902; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892. Leaves of grass; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892—Manuscripts
- Correspondence, 1852-1898 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Letters to and from friends, family members, editors, publishers, and soldiers Whitman met during his time as a nurse in military hospitals in and around Washington, D. C. primarily during the Civil War. However, correspondence is dated both during and after the war.
  - Correspondence to or about Whitman, 1852-1898 and undated, bulk 1860-1892
    Includes letters from friends, family members, and soldiers. Many of the letters have been bound into various scrapbooks and collections of other Whitman papers, and it is advisable to consult the reference archivist with regard to the physical provenance of the material before requesting correspondence in bulk. Material dating past Whitman's death was bound into a volume holding earlier material. Listed alphabetically by author.
    - Bucke, Richard Maurice: To Reuben Farwell (Typescript), 1898 Oct. 14 (Box 17)
      Typescript letter, London, Ont, 14 Oct. 1898, unsigned, requesting any letters by Walt Whitman in his possession.
    - Bucke, Richard Maurice: To Walt Whitman, 1888 Aug. 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Description from Frey: To Walt Whitman, "London, Ont., 17 Aug 1888"; two pages, signed, with an envelope addressed to Whitman by Bucke, and annotated by H. L. Traubel.
    - Bucke, Richard Maurice: To Walt Whitman, 1889 Jan. 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Description from Frey: To the same, "London, Ont., 18 Jan 1889"; two pages, signed. In a board folder.
    - Burroughs, Julian: To Bayard Wyman, undated (Box 2)
      Signed letter, no place, no date, verifying a letter written by Whitman to his parents.
    - Doyle, Peter: To Walt Whitman 1868 Sept. 21 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Washington [D.C.] 21 Sept. 1868; 4-page holograph letter, mentioning early baseball and the trial of the Lincoln conspirators.
    - Farwell, Reuben: To Walt Whitman, 1864 Apr. 30 (Box 17)
      Description from Frey: Eleven autograph letters, signed, thirty-four pages in all; dated as follows: "Camp Stoneman M.d April 30th /64"; "Camp Stoneman May 5th /64"; "Camp Stoneman Oposite Washington City May 10th /64"; "White House Landing V.a June 8th 1864"; "Plymouth Mich. At Home Oct 2d /64"; "Plymouth Mich. Nov 7th 1864"; "Plymouth Mich. Nov. 21th /64"; "Washington City D.C Thursday Eve June 16" (Bucke has added "1865(?)"); "Feb 11th 1875"; "March 5th .75"; "Aug 16th 1875." With typed copies of a letter written by Bucke to Farwell, dated "London, Ont., 14th Oct., 1898," and of an unsigned and undated note written by Whitman to Farwell, annotated by Bucke. Several of Farwell's letters are endorsed in Whitman's autograph. Bound in a small folio volume, cloth, orange morocco back.
    - Farwell, Reuben: To Walt Whitman, 1864 May 5 (Box 17)
    - Farwell, Reuben: To Walt Whitman, 1864 May 10 (Box 17)
    - Farwell, Reuben: To Walt Whitman, 1864 June 8 (Box 17)
    - Farwell, Reuben: To Walt Whitman, 1864 Oct. 2 (Box 17)
    - Farwell, Reuben: To Walt Whitman, 1864 Nov. 7 (Box 17)
    - Farwell, Reuben: To Walt Whitman, 1864 Nov. 21 (Box 17)
    - Farwell, Reuben: To Walt Whitman, [1865?] June 16 (Box 17)
    - Farwell, Reuben: To Walt Whitman, 1875 Feb. 11 (Box 17)
    - Farwell, Reuben: To Walt Whitman, 1875 Mar. 5 (Box 17)
    - Farwell, Reuben: To Walt Whitman, 1875 Aug. 16 (Box 17)
    - Heyde, Charles L.: To Louisa Whitman, 1868 Nov. 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Description from Frey: Autograph letter, "Burlington 24 Nov 1868"; two pages, signed "Charlie." Hannah Heyde has added an unsigned note of two pages.
    - Heyde, Charles L.: To Louisa Whitman, 1868 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Description from Frey: Autograph letter, "Burlington Dec 1868"; three pages, signed. Bucke has added "about 8 Dec."
    - Heyde, Charles L.: To Louisa Whitman, 1852-1873 (Box 5)
      Description from Frey: Seven letters to Mrs. Louisa Whitman, 1852-1873; with sixty-seven autograph letters from C. L. Heyde to Walt Whitman, 1860-1892. Bound in a small folio volume, cloth, blue morocco back.
    - Heyde, Charles L.: To Walt Whitman, 1860-1892 (Box 5)
      Description from Frey: Sixty-seven autograph letters from C. L. Heyde to Walt Whitman, 1860-1892. With 7 letters from Heyde to Louisa Whitman. Bound in a small folio volume, cloth, blue morocco back.
    - Heyde, Hannah Whitman: To Louisa Whitman, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      March 20, no place. Asks mother to take care of herself, then to come stay for the summer. Mentions Walt and George, and her desire to come home. Typescript available.
    - Heyde, Hannah Whitman: To Louisa Whitman, undated (Box 5)
      Burlington [Vt.], no date, letter regarding the abuse she suffers from her husband.
    - Heyde, Hannah Whitman: To Walt Whitman, undated (Box 5)
      Burlington, Vt., 24 Jan. Marked in another hand with date "1892." Urges Whitman to get better, and sends her love.
    - Jennings, William M.: To Walt Whitman, 1890 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Philadelphia, 29 April 1890, requests a sitting for a photograph.
    - Price, Abby H.: To Louisa Whitman, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Description from Frey: Seven autograph letters from Helen E. Price to Mrs. Whitman, twenty-nine pages in all; dated as follows: "Sunday Oct 13th /72"; "New York Nov 24th /72"; "New Years 1873"; "Friday Jan 31st /73"; "Feb 9th /73"; "Saturday," Bucke has added "29 Feb. '73"; "March 27th /73." With one autograph letter, not dated, from Helen's mother, Abby H. Price, to Mrs. Whitman; three pages, signed. Bound in an octavo volume, cloth.
    - Price, Helen E.: To Louisa Whitman, 1872 Oct. 13 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Price, Helen E.: To Louisa Whitman, 1872 Nov. 24 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Price, Helen E.: To Louisa Whitman, 1873 Jan. 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Price, Helen E.: To Louisa Whitman, 1873 Jan. 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Price, Helen E.: To Louisa Whitman, 1873 Feb. 9 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Price, Helen E.: To Louisa Whitman, [1873?], Saturday (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Price, Helen E.: To Louisa Whitman, 1873 Mar. 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Stansberry, Jane, 1874 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Howard Lake, Wright Co., Minn., 15 July 1876. Writes of Whitman's relationship with and letters to her husband, asks his advice regarding pursuing a government pension for him.
    - Stansberry, William: To Walt Whitman, 1873 Dec. 9 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Howard Lake, Wright Co., Minn., 9 Dec. 1873, writes to Whitman of conditions in his state, requests the name of a doctor.
    - Stansberry, William: To Walt Whitman, 1874 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Howard Lake, Wright Co., Minnesota, 12 May 1874; discusses his own and Whitman's health.
    - Stansberry, William: To Walt Whitman, 1874 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Howard Lake [Minn.], 28 June 1874, requests Whitman to visit in order to improve his health.
    - Stansberry, William: To Walt Whitman, 1875 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Howard Lake, Minn., 21 July 1845, requests a loan to assist in finding witnesses in order to obtain a government pension.
    - Van Nostrand, Mary Whitman: To Louisa Whitman, [1875?] Feb. 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Description from Frey: Autograph letter, "Greenport Feb 16"; three pages, signed "Mary."
    - Van Nostrand, Mary Whitman: To Walt Whitman, 1875 Feb. 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Description from Frey: Autograph letter, "Greenport Mar 16," "1875" added in an other hand; four pages, signed, with envelope.
    - Whitman, George: To Louisa Whitman, 1861-1865 (Box 3)
      Description from Frey: A collection of autograph letters, signed in full or with initials, written by George W. Whitman: forty-six are addressed to his mother, eight to Walt Whitman, and one to Thomas Jefferson Whitman. Added to these letters, which were evidently forwarded from one member of the family to another, are five autograph letters and notes by Mrs. Whitman and one by T. J. Whitman, all six addressed to Walt. Most of George's letters carry brief annotations in Walt's autograph indicating the place and date of writing. The dates run from June 28, 1861 to July 14, 1865; 201 pages in all. With one autograph note from Walt to his mother, not dated, and a clipping describing the funeral of George's son, endorsed by Walt: "From the Philadelphia Ledger July 20 1876." Laid in: a tintype of George Whitman and a copy of the report of Major John G. Wright on the activities of the 51st Regiment, New York Volunteers, during the assault on Petersburg, Virgina, July 30, 1864; three pages. In a quarto volume, full blue morocco, gilt tooled.
    - Whitman, George: To Walt Whitman, 1861-1865 (Box 3)
    - Whitman, George: To Thomas Jefferson Whitman, undated (Box 3)
    - Whitman, Louisa: To Walt Whitman, 1860-1868 (Volume 221)
      Description from Frey: A collection of 142 autograph letters from Mrs. Whitman to her son Walt, 1860-1873, about 352 pages; annotated through out by R. M. Bucke. With an autograph note from Walt to his mother, undated, a picture of Mrs. Whitman, and a scrap of paper with the words, "Dearest mother," in Walt's autograph. Bound, with typed transcripts of the letters, in two quarto volumes, full brown morocco, gilt tooled. Also, an extra copy of the transcripts, bound in a quarto volume, cloth, orange morocco back.
    - Whitman, Louisa: To Walt Whitman, 1868-1873 (Volume 222)
    - Whitman, Louisa: Typescript transcription of letters (Box 4)
    - Whitman, Thomas Jefferson: To Walt Whitman, undated
      Conditions Governing Access
      Unavailable
  - Correspondence from or by Whitman, 1861-1892
    Contains letters by friends and family members, editors, publishers, and soldiers. As with the Correspondence to or about Whitman Subseries, many letters in this subseries are bound with other material and the reference archivist should be contacted before correspondence is requested in bulk. Most of Whitman's letters in the Trent Collection date from 1880 to 1891.
    - Bucke, Richard Maurice: 1892 Jan. 27 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Description from Frey: Autograph letter, "Jan 27 noon" [1892]; one page, signed with initials; with envelope.
    - Burroughs, John: 1868 Oct. 22 [?] (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Autograph letter, Providence, R. I., 22 October 1868, discussing his travel plans.
    - Burroughs, John: 1878 July 5
      Description from Frey: Autograph postcard, "1309 Fifth av. 2d house south of 86th St. New York July 5" [1878]; signed with initials. Tipped in H. B. Binns's A Life of Walt Whitman. See: http://search.library.duke.edu/search?id=DUKE000155771
    - Burroughs, John: 1885 June 23 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Description from Frey: Autograph letter, "328 Mickle street Camden New Jersey June 23 '85"; two pages, signed. With an initialled note by Burroughs in the upper righthand corner of the first page.
    - Burroughs, John and Ursula: 1875 Mar. 2 (Box 2)
      Description from Frey: To John and Ursula Burroughs, "431 Stevens st. cor West. Camden N. Jersey. March 2" [ 1875? ]; two pages, signed.
    - Carpenter, Edward: 1877 Oct. 5 (Box 15)
      Description from Frey: Autograph postcard, "Camden New Jersey U S America Oct 5" [1877]; signed with initials.
    - Carpenter, Edward: 1877 Nov. 27 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Description from Frey: Autograph postcard, "Camden New Jersey, U S America Nov 27" [1877]; signed with initials.
    - Carpenter, Edward: 1885 Aug. 5 (Box 2)
      Description from Frey: To Edward Carpenter, "Camden New Jersey U S America Aug 5 '85"; autograph postcard, signed with initials.
    - Contemporary Club, Executive Committee: 1888 Feb. 15 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Description from Frey: Autograph note, "Camden N J Feb: 15 '88," proposing the name of Thomas B. Harned for membership in the Contemporary Club; one page, signed.
    - Cox, George: 1887 June 14 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Autograph postcard, Camden, N. J., 14 June 1887. Whitman notes he has been awaiting proofs which have not arrived. Requests they be sent.
    - Dowden, Edward: 1876 Mar. 4 (Box 2)
      Description from Frey: To Edward Dowden, "431 Stevens st. cor West. Camden, N. Jersey, U. S. America. March 4, /76"; two pages, signed.
    - Doyle, Peter: 1877 July 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Description from Frey: Autograph letter, to "Pete," "Kirkwood New Jersey July 2"; one page, signed "Walt." Bucke has added "(1877)" after the date. With an envelope, addressed by Whitman to Doyle and postmarked "Jun 14."
    - Doyle, Peter: 1880 July 24 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Description from Frey: Autograph postcard, "London Ontario Canada July 24"; signed with initials. Bucke has added "(1880)" after the date.
    - Doyle, Peter: Dec. 20 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Description from Frey: Autograph postcard, "Camden N J Dec 20"; signed with initials.
    - Edmunds, J. M., Postmaster: Nov. 17 (Box 9)
      Description from Frey: A rough draft of a letter, "Nov. 17"; six pages. A request for reconsideration of the postal regulations dealing with the rates on "book manuscripts and corrected proofs passing between authors and publishers." Bound in a small quarto volume, half blue morocco.
    - Eldridge, Charley: 1873 June 23 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Signed "Walt." 322 Steven St, Camden, N.J., 23 June. Writes of being unwell in the head, but getting better, also, of reading Lytton's Kenelm Chillingly.
    - Eldridge, Charley: 1873 July 7 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Signed "Walt." 322 Steven St, Camden, N.J., 23 June. Writes of still suffering pain in the head, requests letters.
    - Eldridge, Charley: 1884 May 7 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Description from Frey: Autograph letter, to "Charley," "328 Mickle street Camden New Jersey May 7 '84"; one page, signed.